This task is about an unbounded Petri net.
And this is the Petri net in question.
And there are several tasks for this Petri
net.
And first of all, we should create part of
the infinite reachability graph.
We cannot create the complete reachability
graph because of course it is infinite.
But the part that we shall create should contain
all states that are reachable within at most
three transitions.
We have to have all the connections between
all possible transitions between these states.
That's what hint also tells us.
Let's switch to another screen.
And here I will draw the reachability graph
now.
This is the Petri net in question still.
We start the reachability graph by using the
initial marking.
We use the usual sequence of places.
s1 is the first, so is the first place of
our tuple.
Second is s2, which has zero tokens.
And third is s3, which has also zero tokens.
The first one has one token at the beginning.
This is the starting point of our reachability
graph.
Now we continue by looking for further transitions
that can happen from there on.
And having in mind that we require all the
connections for firing three transitions.
But when we consider the first marking, well,
the only transition we can fire is t1 because
there's a token in s1.
But the others require tokens in s2 or s3
respectively.
We start by firing t1 and then we get to our
next state.
Let's say we go from here to the next state,
which is zero tokens in s1, because there's
no arrow from t1 going there, but one arrow
going from s1 to t1.
And s2 and s3 will each get one token.
So by firing t1
we have reached this state.
And now we have two options.
There's no token in s1 now, so we cannot fire
t1 when we reach this
marking.
But we can fire t2 as we have got a token in
s2 and we can t3 as we have got a token in
s3.
Basically, it's easy to see which transition
we can fire as in this case for this particular
graph.
Because when there is a token in the first
one, we can fire t1.
When there is a token in the second one, we
can fire t2.
And when there's a token in the third place,
we can fire t3.
We can fire t2.
Let's do this, t2.
And we will get one token in s1 and there
will be no token in s2 left, as one is required
for firing t2.
And we still have the token in s3, as t2 has
no connection to place s3.
And another option for this particular marking
here, this particular state would be firing
t3.
When we fire t3, we would reach the state.
Well, we would reach the state (0,1,2) because
we take one token out of s3, but place two
tokens back in.
This was reached by firing t3.
And we can reach this particular state also
by firing t1, which takes one token from s1
and adds a token to s2 and adds a token to
s3.
This was reached by firing t1.
In this particular case, we would already
be done with firing three transitions, but
we could go from the other states as well.
For instance, we were continuing from here
where we could skip like this.
We can check if there are other options for
this state, for instance, when we are in the
marking where there's one token in s1 and
one token in s3.
And we have already the connection where t1
is fired, but s3 can also be fired.
We would be in a state where there's one more
token in s3 as we take one token and add two
tokens to s3.
We reach the state (1,0,2) by firing t3.
And now we can
continue from this state here because this
is also reachable by two transitions, by firing
t1 and t3.
Thus, we can think about the transitions that
we can fire from here.
And there are two options; we can fire t2,
which takes one token from s2.
And adds a token to s1 which would lead us
to (1,0,2), which is the state we already
have, so we can fire t2 here.
Or we can fire t3, which takes one token from
s3 and adds two tokens to s3, which would
lead us to the state (0,1,3).
Actually, when we now look at this graph,
we can look for all the paths which contain
three transitions.
And we are already done with the task.
You could furthermore add all the edges
that go outside of these
states.
If you have done this, this would be fine
as well.
You could basically just add more edges.
When you think about these states that were
reached, then you can think about what transitions
could be fired from there.
And then these could be added as well, but
this is as I said, optional.
When we think, for instance for this, from
this state here, (1,0,2) we could fire t1
here and we could also fire t2 here.
Let me just draw this down here.
We could fire t1 from here and we could fire
t3.
And from the other state,
from this one here, we could fire t2 and we could
fire t3.
But as I said, this is optional.
Now we could
look at the other task.
Let me just move back to the task again.
And the second task is to explain with the
help of the graph why the net is unbounded
and to describe an infinite sequence of transitions
that leads to an arbitrary large number of
tokens in one of the places of the Petri net.
We can use this reachability graph now.
Or we shall use it as well.
And when we look at it, then we can identify
some places.
Let me just maybe mark this place here.
When we look at two states here, let's say
these two here, then we see that basically
we are in the same state when we are in this
state, as we were before, considering the
tokens available.
The only thing that changed is that we have
got one token more in place three than we
had before here.
But there are the same amount of tokens in
place one, which is one and the same amount
of tokens in place two, which is zero.
But we could fire the same transitions t1
and t2 again.
When doing this, we could basically fire the
sequence t1, t2 repeatedly.
And we would get a sequence which always adds
another token to the place s3.
For instance, if we consider this place here,
this can also be reached by firing t1 and
t2 again, and this would continue.
We could then fire t1 here again and so on.
We could fire t1 and t2 repetitively, and
would always add another token there.
And these considerations could be made for
other places as well.
We could consider doing the same with maybe
some other states.
Well for these two here, maybe we could, for
instance, consider this state here and this
state here.
We could have the sequence t1 and t2 here.
Or we could repetitively have t3 fired here.
Because when we fire t3 again, so firing t3
repeatedly, then we get into this state here.
We can repeat this ever again.
And then we can fire t3 once more, and we
always add another token into place s3.
There are multiple ways of how you can get
such a sequence and you can choose either
one of those.
For instance, firing the sequence of t1 and
t2 repetitively or firing t3, repetitively.
And when you solve the task you have, of course,
to consider those firing sequences using your
reachability graph.
That is by talking about the actual states
in the reachability graph, and then the firing
sequence, which leads to the sequence, which
creates this infinite graph.
Let's go back to the task once more.
And we have done B now and now C is left.
Now we shall modify the Petri net slightly
such that it is no longer unbounded, but it
shall be still deadlock free.
And our change should be as small as possible.
This is the Petri net in question here.
And how can we change this Petri net in order
to make it
bounded but deadlock free?
We can make it bounded, first of all, by changing
this amount here of tokens which are added
into place s3.
When we remove this number and thus change
that there is only one token added to s3,
then we would not be able to generate more
tokens.
Basically, the amount of tokens would not
increase by firing t3 in place s3, but still
it would increase by firing the sequence of
t1 and t2.
Because when we fire t1 and then t2 and then
t1 again, we always, when we fire t1, we add
a token to s3.
And in order to repair this, we can add a
connection between s3 and t2.
If s3 will be a requirement for firing t2,
then this will prevent
generating more tokens in s3.
Because now when we fire t1 and afterwards
fire t2, there will still be one token in
s1.
Now we've made the reachability graph bounded
and also deadlock free.
Because now there will not be a deadlock where
we can do nothing any more.
Because we can always fire t3
or t2 when there are
tokens in s2 or s3.
And in fact, there will be tokens in s2 and
s3 always at the same time.
If there's a token in s2, it will also be
in s3 because when we fire t1 one token is
added to s2 and to s3.
And when we fire t3, we change nothing at
the amount of tokens in s3.
And when we fire t2, both tokens are removed
from s2 and s3.
And so, we are done with this task as well.